Guide to the Samuel Langhorne Clemens Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1860-1962; Series I; 2.3; (7 boxes)
  - Samuel Langhorne Clemens Correspondence
    - Wiggin, Kate Douglas [Mrs. G. C. Riggs], autograph note signed, New York City, 1905 December 6
      Removed from Morse copy of Mark Twain's 70th Birthday: Souvenir (N.Y., 1905).
      Former call number: 53
    - Wright, Mr., photostat of autograph letter signed, Riverdale on the Hudson, 1 page, from original in possession of W. L. Pforzheimer, 1902 January 14
      Former call number: 143.2
    - Wright, William, 4 autograph letters signed to Samuel L. Clemens, Virginia City, Nevada, 15 pages, 1875-1876
      Removed from Morse copy of his History of the Big Bonanza (Hartford, 1876).
      Former call number: 196
    - Yale Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa, autograph letter signed, [New York, N.Y.], 1 page, declining an invitation to speak, mounted on cardboard, 1906 March 3
      Former call number: 198
    - Unidentified correspondent, Hartford, Connecticut, 1 page, expressing disapproval of a man and his work, no year February 22
      Former call number: 173
    - Unidentified correspondent, autograph note signed, written as postscript to a printed form letter: Buffalo, 2 pages, 1870 February 8
      Former call number: 58
    - Unidentified recipient, autograph note, signed, requesting that copy of a publication be sent to Mrs. P. T. Barnum, 1875 October 16
    - Unidentified recipient, autograph notes, signed, requesting watches, May 21 and 30
    - Unidentified recipient, photocopy of an autograph letter, signed, letter of recommendation for Madame Hartwig, 1904 November 16
      Accompanied by a letter to Jacob Blanck from John Howell (March 17, 1967) and a postcard of Twain's writing study in Elmira, New York (undated).
    - Unidentified photographer, autograph note signed, [Elmira, N.Y.?], 1 page, concerning the shipment of a photograph he had ordered, undated
      ANS [to a photographer, i.e., Pach Bros]: [1906].
      Former call number: 187
    - Unidentified printer, autograph note, signed with initials, [Riverdale-on-Hudson], together with printed card of directions, [1901?]
      Former call number: 85
    - Various correspondents, undated
      Contains: 1. 2 autograph letters, signed, to F. E. Bliss, 1897 November 3 - 1901 August 26 (photostats; originals not in Morse collection); 2. Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Clemens, Boston, 1935? November 16, 15 pages [photostat, original not in Morse collection]; 3. 5 autograph letters, signed, to R. W. Gilder, 1898 April 29-1899 August 22 [photostats, originals not in Morse collection].
      Former call number: 75
  - Third Party Correspondence
    - Aldrich, Thomas Bailey, autograph note signed to Mr. Ward, Boston, 1 page, [1880?] June 4 (Box 4)
      Removed from Morse copy of Ferris Greenslet's Life of Aldrich, Cambridge, 1908.
      Former call number: 119
    - Bliss, Frank E.
      - typewritten letter signed to Merle Johnson, Hartford, 1 page, 1910 October 24
        Removed from Morse copy of The Gilded Age (Hartford, 1873).
        Former call number: 130
      - 6 autograph letters signed from William Wright, Virginia City, Nevada, 9 pages, 1875-1876
        Former call number: 195
    - Bliss, Walter, typed letter, signed, to Roswell W. Johnson, with autograph note at bottom of letter in reply, 1915 February 5
    - Chestnutt, Charles W., typed letter, signed, from Roland Phillips, Managing Editor, Harper's Weekly, enclosing invitation to party celebrating Mark Twain's 70th birthday, 1905 December 20
    - Clemens, Clara, 2 autograph letters signed to Muriel Pears, Riverdale, N.Y., and London, 1902 January 21, 1908 June 29
      Includes letters to Pears from Ladies' Home Journal and Albert Bigelow Paine.
      Former call number: 132
    - Clemens, Cyril, various correspondents, 1927-1962
      Contains photocopies of letters from Thomas Edison, Dwight Eisenhower, Ezra Pound, William H. Taft, and Lyndon B. Johnson, as well as copy of a typescript by Willa Cather regarding Twain and an illustration by Jean Cocteau. Also includes photocopies of letters from Mark Twain to Cyril Clemens' parents, Mrs. James Ross Clemens (October 16, 1906) and James Ross Clemens (June 29, 1902).
    - Duneka, F. A., autograph letter signed (positive photostat) from William Dean Howells, 3 pages, concerning S. L. Clemens, 1910 April 27
      Former call number: 192
    - Field, Kate [i.e., Mary Katherine Keemle], autograph letter signed to Major Bittinger, Omaha, Nebraska, 3 pages, autograph note, signed, 1 page, 1891 October 11
      Autograph letter, signed, to Bittinger removed from Morse copy of Lilian Whiting's Kate Field, A Record (Boston, 1899) and autograph note removed from Morse copy of Lilian Whiting's Kate Field (Boston, 1899).
      Former call numbers: 123, 124
    - Ford, Gerald R., typed letter (photocopy), to Mr. Cyril Clemens, 1980 March 14
    - Gillis, Stephen, autograph letter signed (photostat) from Albert Bigelow Paine, Georgetown, Connecticut, 4 pages, negative and positive photostats, 1907 June 12
      Concerning Mark Twain and an inscription written to Stephen Gillis in The Innocents Abroad (1906). Negative and positive photostats of the inscription accompany the leter.
      Former call number: 177
    - Gomme, Geoffrey, typed letter signed and typed postcard signed from Sir Geoffrey Leo Simon Davson, bart., London, England, 2 pages, 1955 November 23, November [i.e., December] 5
      Concerning Elinor Glyn's Mark Twain on Three Weeks (1908). Letter signed: Anthony Glyn.
      Former call number: 186
    - Harper and Brothers Publishers and The Century Co. Publishers, 16 letters, signed for the firm [Harper and Brothers] by John F. Phayre (one note entirely in his handwriting), to Frank E. Bliss, New York City, 1895-1900
      15 of these letters concern the publication of Mr. Clemens's complete works; the final one, the publication of Charles Dudley Warner's. 1 typewritten letter signed by William W. Ellsworth [The Century Co.], secretary, to Frank E. Bliss, N.Y.C., 1899 April 4.
      Former call number: 41
    - Hitchcock, Lucius Wolcott, autograph letter signed to Merle Johnson, New Rochelle, N.Y., 4 pages, 1910 October 1
      Removed from Morse copy of S. L. Clemens's A Horse's Tale (N.Y., 1907).
      Former call number: 129
    - Ladies' Home Journal, typed letter signed by W. V. Alexander as managing editor, to Muriel Pears, Philadelphia
      Related Materials
      See: Clemens, Clara
      Former call number: 134
    - Linton, William James, autograph note signed to Edmund Clarence Stedman, New Haven, 1 page, 1878 June 8
      Removed from the Morse copy of Lotos Leaves (Boston, 1875).
      Former call number: 126
    - Lyon, I. V., autograph note signed to Messrs.Harper and Brothers, New York City, 1 page, typewritten letter signed to the Reverend L. M. Powers, Redding, Connecticut, 2 pages, to Clemens, 1906 April 2, 1908 December 23
      Removed from Morse copy of Mark Twain's Stolen White Elephant (Boston, 1882) and Mark Twain's Burke on Croker and Tammany.
      Former call numbers: 121, 122
    - Matthews, Brander
      - 2 autograph letters signed to [Erastus] Brainerd, New York City, 4 pages each, 1880 December 8, 1881 September 14
        Removed from Morse copy of his Essays on English (N.Y., 1921).
        Former call number: 117
      - autograph note signed to [Frank E.] Bliss, New York City, 1 page, 1899 January 22
        Former call number: 118
    - Merrill, Frank Thayer, autograph letter signed to Merle De Vore Johnson, Dorchester, Massachusetts, 2 pages, 1910 October 17
      Removed from Morse copy of S. L. Clemens's Prince and the Pauper (Boston, 1882).
      Former call number: 131
    - Nixon, F.B., autograph letter, signed, to Frank Fuller, 1894 February 24 and 28
      Includes "Abstract of Mark Twain's Lecture on 'Sandwich Islands,' Delivered in St. Louis, March 25th, 1867," typescript.
    - Opper, Frederick Burr, autograph note signed from Albert Bigelow Paine, autograph manuscript (positive photostat) of "Cowards," with inscription (also photostat), Christmas 1916, and initialed identification: "One of Mark Twain's notes. A.B.P."
      The note includes an autograph of "Cowards," written by Mark Twain.
      Former call number: 184
    - Paine, Albert Bigelow, autograph letter signed to Muriel Pears, Washington, D.C.
      Former call number: 133
    - Reid, Whitelaw, autograph note signed to Edmund Clarence Stedman, New York City, 1 page, 1881 December 27
      Former call number: 127
    - Riley, James Whitcomb, autograph note signed to Chester S. Lord, Indianapolis, 1 page, 1900 November 6
      Removed from Morse copy of Speeches at the Lotos Club (N.Y., 1901).
      Former call number: 116
    - Smith, Mrs. Albert M., typed letter signed from B[arney]. C. M. Faisthing, Paris, MO, 1 leaf, with addressed envelope, concerns Mark Twain, 1910 July 3
      Former call number: 153
    - Trumbull, Annie and Mrs. James Hammond Trumbull, 7 autograph letters signed from Olivia Clemens, 2 incomplete, 1883-1903
      Former call number: 148
    - Trumbull, Annie
      - typed letter signed from Clara Clemens, Hollywood, Calif., 1897-1948
        The 4th leaf is a separate typed letter signed to Annie Trumbull and from Clara Clemens. This letter is dated 1948 March 30. Includes autograph letter signed from Joseph Hopkins Twichell, Minerva, N.Y., to Annie Trumbull and Mrs. James Hammond Trumbull.
        Former call number: 149
      - autograph letter signed from William Lyon Phelps, New Haven, undated
        Former call number: 150
      - typed letter signed from Wilbur Lucius Cross, Hartford, Conn., 1 leaf, 1935 July 17
    - Twichell, Joseph H., autograph letter signed from Joseph Roswell Hawley, Washington, D.C., 4 pages, 1887 January 29
      Included among Clemens's letters to Twichell, but appears to have no connection with them. Possibly sent by Twichell to Clemens and returned by him.
      Former call number: 160
    - Warner, Charles Dudley
      - autograph letter signed to Thomas Wentworth Higginson, Hartford, 2 pages, 1873 December 31
        Removed from Morse copy of The Gilded Age (Hartford, 1873). Includes engraved portrait, with his autograph signature written on a separate slip and pasted below. Removed from Morse copy of The Gilded Age (Hartford, 1873).
        Former call numbers: 112, 113
      - autograph letter signed to Mr. Simmons, Hartford, 2 pages [photostat of original letter laid in], 1873 February 9
        Removed from Morse copy of S. L. Clemens's Innocents Abroad (Hartford, 1869).
        Former call number: 114
      - autograph inscription, polite sentiment written for autograph hunter, with full signature, 1895 October 12
        Former call number: 115
    - Wector, Dixon, typed letter, signed, to Jacob Blanck, enclosing typed copy of Mark Twain's "Some Thoughts on the Science of Onanism, Address to the Stomach Club, Paris, 1879", 1947 October 6
    - Whitmore, F., autograph letter, signed, to William Clemens, 1892 May 27
    - Windmüller, Louis, autograph letters, signed, to Mr. Munro, 1898
  - Willard S. Morse Correspondence
    - General "A-Z" (Box 5)
    - Beard, Daniel Carter
      - General correspondence, 1915- 1925
      - Typewritten letter signed to Morse, Flushing, L.I., 2 pages, 1915 April 9
        Removed from Morse copy of S. L. Clemens's Connecticut Yankee, N.Y., 1889.
        Former call number: 135
    - Brownell, George Hiram, 1871- 1934; 2
      Includes typescripts: "Back-Tracking Mark Twain," 1-70; "Newspapers: Containing First Printings of Writings by Mark Twain," 1-21; "Periodicals Containing First Printing of Writings by Mark Twain," 1-17; "Newspapers: Containing News Articles, Editorials, Interviews, Anecdotes and Miscellaneous Material About Mark Twain," 1-3; "Newspapers: Containing Writings by Mark Twain," 1-18; "Samuel L. Clemens -- Antiquarian," 1-4.
    - Chapin, Roberta S., 1931-1932
    - Christ, Reverend Frederick V.
      - Autograph note signed from Selma Ottiliana Lovisa Lagerlöf, 1 page, 1919 December 2
        Former call number: 139
      - Typed letter signed from Amy Lowell, in the handwriting of her secretary, Brookline, Massachusetts, [sent by Mr. Christ to Willard S. Morse], 1920 February 28
        Former call number: 140
      - 7 autograph letters signed to Morse, Scranton and Hollidaysburg, PA, [1921]-[1927]
        Also included is a typewritten letter from James Moore, secretary to Mr. Morse, to Christ, dated 1921 March 29; Rev. Frederick V. Christ, Lecture of, "Mark Twain's Demon," Letter of Samuel L. Clemons, August 28, 1908, Scranton, Penn.; news clippings from Scranton, PA, Republican, 1921 January [24?], 31, "All Twain's Ideas Secured Outside" and "'Mark Twain's Demon' is Lecture Theme." As well as a sketch of Mark Twain in a letter from Morse and a Christmas card ("Dear Friend:") from Christ with the handwritten note, "I have not forgotten you."
        Former call number: 141
    - Clemens, Cyril, 1924-1935
    - Clemens, William M., 1915-1916
      Includes profile of Samuel Clemens published in "Routledge's 'Men of the Time,'" annotated by the author.
    - Connecticut State Library, Hartford, 1931-1935
    - Cook, Charles C., 1931-1935
    - Dawson, Ernest, "Mark Twain Manuscripts," 2 volumes; "List of Mark Twain's Books Autographed by Him", undated
    - Foley, P. K., 1912
    - Garvie, Billy S., autograph letter signed to Willard S. Morse, Hartford, Connecticut, [1934?] August 2
    - Ginn, Frank H., 1910-1920
    - G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1918 May 13-17
    - Hankemeyer, Mrs., autograph letter signed from Morse, Santa Monica, California, 1 leaf, 1930 April 21 (Box 6)
    - Hankemeyer, Frances N., 1930-1933
    - Hannibal, typed letters signed from F. J. Russell, Hannibal Mark Twain Centennial, Hannibal, Missouri, 1935 February 23-May 13
    - Harper & Brothers, 1907- 1918
    - Howell, John, typed letter signed to Willard S. Morse, 1927 September 29
    - Hutton, Laurence, autograph note, signed, to E. H. Goss, Sorrento, Italy, 1893 March 28
      Removed from Morse copy of Laurence and Eleanor Hutton: Their Books of Association (New York, 1905).
    - James, George Wharton, 1918 February 1-July 20
    - Johnson, Merle, undated, 1935 July 5
      Includes typed letter, signed, from Jacob Blanck to Willard S. Morse, 1935 July 5.
    - Johnson, Robert Underwood, autograph note signed to Morse, [New York City], 1 page, 1915 September 14
      Former call number: 136
    - King, C. Archibald, 1916- 1918
    - Leach, Mrs. Frank S., 1922- 1923
    - London Anti Vivisection Society, typed letters, signed, 1914-1915
    - Mahan, George A., 1917- 1931
    - Merriam, G. & C. Company, 1915- 1916
    - Missouri State Historical Society, mostly letters from Floyd C. Shoemaker to Morse, 1930-1935
      Also includes correspondence from Stella M. Drumm and Roy T. King.
    - Paine, Albert Bigelow, 1910-1920
      Also includes typed letter signed to Merle Johnson.
    - Phillips, Catherine (Coffin), 2 autograph letters signed to Morse, [Los Angeles], 4 pages each, 1928 September 13, 1929 March 7
      Former call number: 137
    - Rushmore, A. W., typed letter signed to Merle Johnson, 1920 May 25
    - Smith, Grant H., 9 typed letters signed to Willard S. Morse, 1933 June 5-November 13
    - Starrett, Vincent, 2 autograph letters signed to Morse, 1 typed letter signed to Morse, 4 typed letters to Starrett, 1918 June 19-July 19
    - Steindorff, Ulrich L., 1 typed letter to Steindorff from Morse, 2 typed letters signed to Morse from Steindorff, 1 autograph letter signed to Morse from Steindorff (with clipping from L. A. Times ), 1924- 1935
      Correspondence concerning Mark Twain's translation of Heinrich Hoffmann's Der Struwwelpeter.
    - Tufts, James, 10 typed letters to Tufts, 14 autograph letters signed to Morse, 1917-1928
    - Underhill, Irving S., 1927-1933
    - Woodward & Lothrop, Inc. (Fred E. Woodward), 1912-1919
    - Wyeth, Newell Convers, autograph letter signed to Morse, Chadds Ford, PA, 2 pages, 1919 November 25
      Removed from Morse copy of S. L. Clemens's Mysterious Stranger (N.Y., 1916).
      Former call number: 138
  - Walter Francis Frear Correspondence
    - Branch, Mr., autograph letter, to Branch, no year September 23 (Box 7)
    - Brown, Arthur F., typed letter, to Brown, 1939
    - Brownell, George Hiram, typed letters, signed, to Frear, with replies, autograph manuscript and typed, 1936-1942
    - Connecticut Historical Society, typed letter, signed, to Frear, 1938-1939
    - Connecticut State Library, typed letter, signed, to Frear, 1940
    - DeVoto, Mr., typed letter, signed, to Frear, and autograph letter, in reply, 1942
    - Frank Glenn, Bookseller, typed letter, signed, to Frear, 1943
    - Hartford Public Library (Connecticut), typed letter, signed, from Frear, 1938
    - Morse, Alma B., autograph letter, signed, 1942
    - Queen's University (Canada) and The Gazette (Montreal), 1935
    - Schisler, H. Reginald, typed letter, signed, to Frear, 1942
    - State Historical Society of Missouri, typed letter, signed, to Frear, 1938
    - Wilder, E. W., typed letter, signed, to Frear, 1942
- Writings, 1870-1968; Series II; 5.63; (15 boxes)
  Series II is organized into three subseries: Writings by Mark Twain, Contracts and Agreements, and Writings of Others.
  The series documents Clemens's writing career from 1860 until his death in 1910, as well as the posthumous publication of his writings. Autograph manuscripts can be found in the collection for The Gilded Age, My Debut as a Literary Person, Clemens's translation of Der Struwwelpeter into English, and A Tramp Abroad. Materials relating to the illustration of Clemens's writing can also be found in the collection; this includes original drawings by C. H. Warren and F. M. Senior for Puddn'head Wilson and original illustrations, and prints on which the illustrations are based, for A Tramp Abroad. Contracts, agreements, and Clemens's notes on international copyright (located in Series IV, Other Papers), illustrate Clemens's interest in his intellectual property rights and the management of his literary estate.
  The subseries Writings of Others contains a catalogue of Willard S. Morse's collection and scholarship on Clemens.
  - Writings by Samuel Langhorne Clemens
    - "1601," or, "Conversation at the Social Fireside as it Was in the Time of the Tudors," typescript, photostat, 1960s (Box 8)
    - An Addition to the Private History of the "Jumping Frog" Story, New York, 1900, 1918
      Includes autograph letters to Frank E. Bliss, written in the margins of a sheet of page-proof, and on a separate slip of paper: London, 1900 March 30.
      Former call number: 19
    - The Adventures of Tom Sawyer
      - "Notes for Cemetery Scene," original manuscript, undated
        Published in American Literature, xxxii, 4 (Jan 1961) in footnote on page 384 of "The composition and the Structure of Tom Sawyer," by Hamlin L. Hill, off-print unit manuscript. Removed from Aldis copy of his Huckleberry Finn (London, 1884).
        Former call number: 168
      - Miscellaneous type-settings for title-pages and pages of text, proofs of illustrations in various states, proofs of printed pages, 1939
        Accompanied by correspondence of George Macy, Carl Purington Rollins, Thomas Hart Benton, and Sidney A. Kimber regarding the edition of this book published in 1940 by the Limited Edition Club, Inc., New York City. 65 letters and copies of letters.
    - "After-Dinner Speech," [at a fourth-of-July gathering, in London, of Americans.], original manuscript of speech delivered July 4, 1872, 1872 July 4
      Former call number: 25
    - Colonel Sellers, A Play, by Mark Twain and William Dean Howells, typescript, [102] leaves, with manuscript corrections and additions by Mark Twain and a few manuscript notes by W. D. Howells, undated
      The character of Col. Sellers was taken from The Gilded Age. A scene from the play was used as the basis for a section of The American Claimant.
      Former call number: 3
    - "Concerning the American Language," autograph manuscript of "part of a chapter which was crowded out of A Tramp Abroad ", undated
      Former call number: 7
    - "Constitution and Laws of the Juggernaut Club," typewritten manuscript, signed, sent by him to Muriel Pears, according to her note, with manuscript additions, 4 pages, 1902 December 15
      Former call number: 99
    - "Doggerel," autograph manuscript, 2 pages, 2 four-line stanzas, undated
      Former call number: 82
    - Europe and Elsewhere, galley-proofs, with manuscript note in unidentified handwriting, "one of 10 sets pulled." Published New York, 1923, 129 sheets
      Former call number: 1
    - "Following the Equator," 1 manuscript page of notebook, 1 manuscript chapter heading, 15 miscellaneous photographs, clippings, and facsimiles with manuscript directions and notes of explanation, undated
      Also includes 1 autograph letter signed to Frank E. Bliss, London, March 26, 1897.
      Former call number: 4
    - The Gilded Age
      - Autograph manuscript, leaves 613-622, 622 1/2, 623-635, 1021-1038, and "map of the Salt Lick Branch of the Pacific R.R.," original drawing by Clemens, with corresponding pages from first edition (Hartford, 1874) (Box 9)
        Former call number: 2
      - Autograph manuscript, leaves 136-139, 2 leaves in the hand of Clemens, 2 in that of C. D. Warner, and corresponding pages (62-64) from first edition (Hartford, 1874)
        Former call number: 8
      - Autograph manuscript, leaves 537-568, leaves numbered in the hand of C. D. Warner, corresponding pages (217-227) from first edition (Hartford, 1874)
        Former call number: 10
      - Autograph manuscript, leaves 673-692, corresponding pages (264-273) from first edition (Hartford, 1874), undated
        Former call number: 11
      - Autograph manuscript, [127] leaves, incomplete: 64 leaves in the hand of Clemens; 63 in that of C. D. Warner. Leaves numbered 3-5, 33, 55, 101, 105-6, 132-3, 141, 163, 167, 174, 269, 281-2, 284, 288, 306, 310, 315, 336, 348, 428, 431, 441, 449, 576, 579-82, 584-7, 589, 612, 725, 729, 799-800, 803, 815, 838, 890, 894, 905, 927, 1003, 1013-14, 1020, 1039, 1042, 1044, 1048-50, 1055-7, 1060, 1067-9, 1071-5, 1098, 1105, 1107-10, 1137, 1141-5, 1147, 1149-51, 1183, 1197, 1204-[06], 1208-9, 1211, 1238-51, 1254, 1281, 9 (1282), 1292, 1315-16, 1319-21, 1324, 1330-31, 1334, 1422, 1447, 1455-7, leaves 146 and 1199 (Clemens) and 1454 (Warner): positive photostats, from originals in the library of the University of Wisconsin, undated
        Former call number: 12b
      - Autograph manuscript, leaves 324-325, corresponding to passages on pages 119-120 in the first edition of the book, a joint production of Warner and S. L. Clemens, undated
        Former call number: +205
      - Chapter Headings: autograph manuscript, with corrected proofs: [62] leaves. Incomplete., undated
        Former call number: 21
        Prepared for the first edition (Hartford, 1874) of The Gilded Age, by Mark Twain and Charles Dudley Warner. The headings for chapters 21, 23, 38, 40, and 44 are in the hand of C. D. Warner. Translations: autograph manuscript: [33] leaves, prepared for the Autograph edition (Hartford, 1899) of The gilded age, by Mark Twain and Charles Dudley Warner.
      - Autograph manuscript, chapters 14, 16, 21, accompanied by envelopes addressed to The Wheeler Publishing Company from Merwin Gray & Company (postmarked 1917), undated, 1917
        Former call number: 204
      - Autograph manuscript (photocopy), pages 1410, 1444, undated
        Former call number: 33
      - Illustration, "There's Millions In It," copyright J. P. Soule, and signed, "Hooper", 1877